Guide to the Elisha Camp papers, 1756-1879.
Camp, Elisha papers, 1756-1879.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Elisha Camp papers, 1756-1879.
696
Elisha Camp.
7.2 cubic ft.; 9 v.
Correspondence; accounts; contracts; leases; surveys; bonds; deeds; receipts; other land, legal, and business papers; political broadsides; pamphlets; editorials; handbills; and speeches.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers pertaining to the early history of Jefferson County, New York.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Postmaster, militia officer, lawyer, deputy New York State district attorney, politician, newspaper owner and editor, banker, landowner, and land agent.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, accounts, contracts, leases, surveys, bonds, deeds, receipts, and other land, legal, and business papers, political broadsides and pamphlets pertaining to the early history of Jefferson County, New York, particularly on the township of Hounsfield, on the transfer of land from intermediate investors to actual settlers, on the attempts to make Sackets Harbor a great commercial center, and on the accompanying economic, political, and social developments. Collection is chiefly concerned with Camp, who served as representative of his brother-in-law Augustus Sacket, and for other absentee landowners such as David A. Ogden, Thomas L. Ogden, Peter Kemble, Ezra Hounsfield, Lemuel Storrs, Henry Champion, Herman LeRoy, William Bayard, James M. Ellis, Cornelius Ray, Michael Hogan, James Le Ray Chaumont, the executors of the Nicholas Olive estate and the executors of Nicholas Gouvernor. Papers after 1845 are chiefly family letters between Camp and his children and Elisha E. Camp who was in Mexico (1847), Green Bay, Wisconsin, Washington Territory, and Oregon, and a series of Civil War letters. Names of persons and firms represented include David Boyd, President James Buchanan, DeWitt Clinton, James C. Duane, George Hale, L. Seymour, Gerrit Smith, Jesse C. Smith, Charles Smyth, Joseph C. Yates, the Jefferson County Agricultural Society, Jefferson County Bank, Lake Ontario Steamboat Co., Ogden Land Co., and the Sackets Harbor and Ellisburgh Railroad.
Other topics include the Sackets Harbor and Saratoga Railroad, Sackets Harbor Steam and Ferry Boat Co., Union Academy, and the Watertown and Rome Railroad. Also, handbills, editorials, and speeches concerning National Republican Party politics on the New York State and local levels, and containing uncomplimentary references to the Bucktail faction. Other papers pertain to the militia system, the United States Navy, restrictive fees on Lake Ontario commerce, and water rights at Brownville, New York.
Detailed list available in accession folder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Camp, Elisha.; Bayard, William.; Boyd, David.; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868.; Camp family.; Camp, Elisha E.; Champion, Henry.; Clinton DeWitt, 1769-1828.; Duane, James C.; Ellis, James M.; Gouverneur, Nicholas.; Hale, George.; Hogan, Michael.; Hounsfield, Ezra.; Kemble, Peter.; Le Ray de Chaumont, J. (James), 1760-1841.; LeRoy, Herman.; Ogden, David A.; Ogden, Thomas L.; Olive, Nicholas.; Ray, Cornelius.; Sacket, Augustus.; Seymour, L.; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Smith, Jesse C.; Smyth, Charles.; Storrs, Lemuel.; Yates, Joseph C.; Jefferson County (N.Y.) Agricultural Society.; Jefferson County Bank.; Lake Ontario Steamboat Co.; New York (State). Militia.; Ogden Land Company.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Sackets Harbor and Ellisburgh Railroad.; Sackets Harbor and Saratoga Railroad.; Sackets Harbor Bank.; Sackets Harbor Steam and Ferry Boat Company.; Union Academy.; United States. Navy.; Watertown and Rome Railroad.
Subjects:
Inland water transportation--New York (State)--Jefferson County.; Land titles--Valuation.; Land titles--Exchange of.; Mills and mill-work--New York (State)--Jefferson County.; Politics, Practical--New York (State)--Jefferson County.; Shipping--New York (State)--Jefferson County.; Manufactures--New York (State)--Jefferson County.
Places:
Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Social conditions.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Economic aspects.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--Finance.; Sackets Harbor (N.Y.)--Commerce.; Sackets Harbor(N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; Sackets harbor (N.Y.)--Social conditions.; Sackets Harbor (N.Y.)--Finance.; Jefferson County (N.Y.)--History, Local.; Hounsfield (N.Y.)--History.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.; Leases.; Surveys.; Bonds (negotiable instruments).; Deeds.; Broadsides.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a PDF finding aid with more detailed information about the collection.
  All the material in the collection may not be covered by this guide.
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., June 28, 1756; 1784-1818 (Box 1)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1818-1822 (Box 2)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1822-1827 (Box 3)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1827-1830 (Box 4)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1831-1833 (Box 5)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1834-1835 (Box 6)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1836-1837 (Box 7)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1837-1839 (Box 8)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1840-1842 (Box 9)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1842-1845 (Box 10)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1846-1850 (Box 11)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1850-1853 (Box 12)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1854-1855 (Box 13)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1856-1859 (Box 14)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., 1860, undated (Box 15)
- Letters, legal documents, receipts, etc., undated (Box 16)
- Ms. drafts of political handbills, editorials, and speeches (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous political drafts, undated (Box 18)
- Scrapbook, 1820-1838 (Volume 1)
- Day Book, 1838-1841 (Volume 2)
- Day Book, 1840-1846 (Volume 3)
- Account Book, 1817-1821 (Volume 4)
- Account Book, 1835 (Volume 5)
- Account Book, 1846-1847 (Volume 6)
- Shipping Book, 1847-1860 (Volume 7)
- Ledger, 1816-1845 (Volume 8)
- Business Letter Book - signed by Camp as cashier; seems to be banking, 1855-1856 (Volume 9)
- Plan of proposed division of Sackets Harbor, 1823 (Folder 1)